第五集：鸟类
1.5亿年前
One 150 million years ago,
就在恐龙达到它们繁盛时期时
as dinosaurs approached their golden age,
有一类生物却朝着一个全新的方向演化
one group evolved along new and revolutionary lines.
尽管仍然保留着某些爬行动物的特征
Although they retained many of their reptilian characteristics,
但它们已经具备全新的
they acquired extraordinary new ones...
羽毛
..feathers.
羽毛帮助保温、隔热
Feathers helped with insulation
展示（鸟类都爱秀）
and display.
但羽毛能提供更有价值的东西
But they offered something far more valuable.
飞翔的力量
The power of flight.
对鸟来说，这改变了一切
And for birds,that changed everything.
鸟类在空中享有自由，比其它任何动物都跑得更快、更远
Birds have the freedom of the skies,to travel
further and faster than any other group of animals
能在地球每一个角落获得机会
and to seize opportunities in all corners of the planet.
但鸟类也必须在生命中的一些关键时刻
But this freedom brings many survival challenges,
应付由这种自由带来的生存挑战
which birds must tackle at pivotal moments in their lives.
飞翔需要极高的技巧和力量
Flying demands enormous skill and effort,
秘鲁安第斯山麓，没哪里比在这里更明显了
and nowhere is that more evident than here,
in the foothills of the Peruvian Andes.
这只雌性蜂鸟能在吸食花蜜时，稳稳地悬停在空中
This female hummingbird hovers with
precision in her quest for nectar.
它翅膀和尾巴的构造，能让它朝任何方向飞
Her wing and tail design allow her to fly in any direction.
但雄性在飞翔时却有问题
But the male has a real problem flying.
这是由于
And this is why
它被两根超长的尾羽所压，就像绑着两个沉重的盘
he's weighed down with two super-long tail
feathers,tipped with cumbersome discs.
这就是不可思议的凤尾蜂鸟
This is the marvellous spatuletail hummingbird.
这两根长羽毛也是它吸引异性的招牌
and these are his flags with which to seduce a mate.
来回地舞动它们要花费很多的气力
Waving them back and forth takes a lot of effort,
即使是在舒适的栖息场所
even from the comfort of his perch,
但为了赢得她的芳心，它必须一直努力
but to win her heart he's got to go up a gear.
必须证明自己是多么善于飞翔，即便这是件苦差
He must show her how well he can fly but it's exhausting work.
由于非常辛苦，它只能腾空几秒钟
It's so demanding he can only stay airborne for a matter of seconds
然后休息一下
before he needs a rest.
它努力想打动她，作出最后一次尝试
He's struggling to impress her,so one last try.
由于极度的耗费体力，蜂鸟只进行短暂的爆发式的飞行
The extreme effort and energy needed to hover means
hummingbirds can only fly in short, sharp bursts.
但大部分的鸟需要在空中停留很长时间
But most birds need to stay
airborne for considerably longer,
必须找到更为节省体力的方式
and must find far more energy-efficient ways to get around.
在埃塞俄比亚的Simien山脉
Here in the Simien mountains of Ethiopia,
海拔15000英尺的地方
at a breathtaking altitude of 15000 feet,
生活着一种空中大师
lives a supreme aerial maestro.
髭兀鹰
The lammergeier.
这头幼鹰乘着从山谷升上来的气流滑翔
This youngster glides on air currents
rising from the mountain slopes below.
它长达9英尺的翼展，能带它每天飞行几百英里
His nine-foot wingspan can carry him hundreds of miles a day
寻找动物的尸体，却花费极少的力气
in search of animal carcasses,with precious little effort.
它警惕着其它的空中拾荒者，如这只狮鹫
He watches out for other airborne
scavengers,like these griffon vultures.
它们与它在悬崖上造成了一些混乱，或许是个进食的机会
They lead him to some commotion on the cliffs,
and maybe the chance to feed.
但这头幼鹰并非唯一发现这个机会的
But this youngster is not the only
lammergeier to spot the opportunity.
这头成年鹰也有份
So too has this adult.
秃鹫们很快将尸体吃光了
The vultures quickly strip the carcass clean.
看起来它太晚了，实际上抵达时间刚好
It seems he's too late. But in fact
he's timed his arrival perfectly.
一丁点儿肉都不剩
There's no meat left
这正是髭兀鹰所期待的时刻
and that's exactly the moment that the
lammergeier has been waiting for.
它图的是那些骨头
It's bones he's after.
年幼的髭兀鹰也来到这具尸体
The young lammergeier too homes in on the carcass.
骨头富含骨髓和油脂
Bones contain rich marrow fat,
但要得到它们并不容易
but extracting it is not easy,
尤其是骨头重达4公斤，很坚硬，无法吞下
especially when the bone is a solid
four kilos and too big to swallow.
但是髭兀鹰有一种奇特的方法，这多亏它们的飞行技能
But lammergeiers have an extraordinary solution,
thanks to their flying skills.
将骨头抓起，乘着热气流飞起来
Soaring up on thermal air currents and positioning the bone parallel
它很快就爬到了一个完美的高度
to his body to minimize drag,he soon reaches the perfect height.
从这里滑翔至一个合适的地方
From here he glides to a place he knows
让它可以处理骨头
where he can deal with the bone,
那里悬崖边上，有一块巨大的石板
where there are giant rock slabs sit on the lip of an escarpment.
骨头撞碎了
The bone is smashed.
它的胃液酸性比蓄电池里的液体还要高
The juices in his stomach are more corrosive than battery acid.
能够溶解骨头，以便消化吸收骨髓
They dissolve the bone so that he can now digest the marrow.
其它的则过来寻找剩下的
Others come looking for leftovers.
但它们时机不好
But their timing isn't ideal
因为现在轮到幼年髭兀鹰了
because now the young lammergeier has his turn!
它们最好服从领导
They'd better mind their heads!
熟练地丢骨头需要不断地练习
Proficient bone smashing takes endless practice
找到最佳的高度、速度和松手时机
to find just the right height,speed and moment of release.
髭兀鹰有宽大的翅膀
Lammergeiers have long, broad wings,
能以最大的效率滑翔很远
ideal for gliding great distances with maximum efficiency.
但在加勒比海的小多巴哥岛上
But on the island of Little Tobago in the Caribbean
生活着一种对飞行敏捷程度要求更高的鸟
lives a bird for whom aerial agility
is of paramount importance.
红嘴热带鸟
The red-billed tropicbird.
短小而尖的翅膀给了它们灵活性和速度
Short, pointed wings give it
great manoeuvrability and speed.
在繁育期，它们的飞行技巧遇到了终极挑战
During the breeding season,
these flying skills are tested to the limit.
当一方照看幼鸟时，另一方必须外出
While one parent looks after the chick, the other must journey
远离崖壁，在水面捕捉小鱼和小乌贼
far offshore, to gather small fish
and squid from the surface waters.
但最困难的是将食物送回来，因为它们与强盗为临
But the hardest part is getting food back to the island,
because they share this airspace with thieves.
强壮的军舰鸟
Magnificent frigatebirds,
人称鸟中战士，在高空巡视
known as Man O' War birds,patrol high above.
这些海盗并不杀死热带鸟
These pirates are not trying to kill the tropicbird,
但会逼迫它们放弃到嘴的食物
but force it to give up its catch.
这是一场激烈的空战
It's an aerial dogfight.
热带鸟在转弯时更快
Tropicbirds are quicker on the turn.
军舰鸟的身体比例非常完美
Frigates have exceptionally lightweight bodies
超长的翼展给了它们巨大的力量
and their extremely long wings give them great power.
成功了
Success.
它们最喜欢在后面从高处袭击
A favourite attack is from behind,and at height.
鱼在那儿
There goes the fish -
另一个胜利
another victory.
这只小热带鸟仍然在等待
This tropicbird chick still
awaits the return of its parent
正在遭受海盗打劫的亲人的归来
who has yet to run the gauntlet of the pirates.
尽量接近海面是它最好的选择
Keeping close to the waves is his best chance.
军舰鸟的羽毛里含油很少
Frigatebirds have so little oil in their feathers
它们不敢落在水面
they can't risk ditching.
如果它刚好能赶到崖壁，就安全了
If he can just reach the cliffs he'll be safe.
它做到了，带回满嘴的鱼
He's made it,with his crop still full of fish.
红嘴热带鸟依靠敏捷度极高的飞行
Red-billed tropicbirds rely on extreme aerial agility
克服了生活中的许多挑战
to overcomethe many challenges of their life.
对另一些鸟来说，生存需要忍耐力
For others,survival demands endurance.
每个春天，红腹滨鹬
Every spring, red knots
会从阿根廷的越冬场所飞行10000英里到加拿大的筑巢地点
fly 10,000 miles from their wintering grounds
in Argentina to their nesting sites in Canada.
完成这种马拉松式旅程的唯一方法
The only way they complete this marathon journey
是要在位于美国东海岸的特拉华海湾,作一次重要的停留休整
is by making a crucial fuel stop here in
Delaware Bay,on the east coast of America.
最为奇妙的是，在找到这个地点的同时
What is most extraordinary is that
as well as having to find their way
它们必须在抵达时机上也要恰到好处
to this one location, they must also
time their arrival to perfection.
它们同海水深处的一种史前生物有个约会
They have a rendezvous with prehistoric
creatures emerging from the deep
近2.5亿年来一直没变
which have hardly changed in 250 million years.
它们在每年春潮最高时蜂拥而至
They come ashore in greatest numbers
on the highest spring tides.
鲎
Horseshoe crabs.
鲎在这里产卵
The crabs are here to lay their eggs.
这也是红腹滨鹬们所追寻的
That's what the knots are after.
大多数的卵被埋起来吃不到
Most eggs are buried out of reach,
但有些卵意外地被其它的鲎挖出来了
but some are accidentally dug up by other crabs.
绝大部分的西大西洋红腹滨鹬加入了这场疯狂地宴会
Most of the west Atlantic red knot
population join this feeding frenzy.
这是红腹滨鹬重新储存脂肪的关键几周
In a matter of weeks the knots need
to rebuild their fat reserves
体重倍增
and double in weight.
为了达成指标，每只红腹滨鹬要吃掉40万只卵
To achieve this, each knot
must eat as many as 400,000 eggs -
这对每次只能吞下一只的它们来说，是个离谱的数字
a tall order given the skill and
effort needed to swallow just one.
埋头不停地进食，意味着很难防范天敌
Head down, feeding non-stop means
it's hard to be alert to predators.
游隼
A peregrine falcon.
产完卵后，鲎离开了海岸
With egg laying complete,the horseshoe crabs now leave
红腹滨鹬会吃掉所有它们能找到的卵
these shores while the knots
gather every last egg they can find.
鸟儿们该上路了
It's time for the birds to move on.
接下来它们会有个2000英里的无间歇飞行
The knots still have a further 2,000-mile non-stop flight
最终到达加拿大的繁育场所
to reach their breeding grounds in Canada.
飞翔给了鸟类很多优势，但这也有句点
Flight gives birds many advantages,
but there's a period in their lives
当它们必须回到地面时
when they are forced back down to Earth.
繁育期
The nesting season.
这是它们最为冒险的时期
This is the time when they are at most risk,
所以它们必须寻找尽可能安全的地方
so they must find the safest possible location.
极少有像火烈鸟这样极端的
Few go to greater extremes than lesser flamingos.
它们在非洲偏僻的盐碱湖筑巢
They nest in the remotest corners
of Africa's caustic soda lakes.
就像它们的爬行类祖先，所产的卵是不透水的
Like their reptilian ancestors,birds lay waterproof eggs.
尽管如此，火烈鸟依旧
Despite this,flamingos still protect theirs
将巢穴筑在湖水淹不到的特殊的泥堆上
on special mud-stack nests as the lake is prone to flooding.
这里也会凉爽一些
It's also just a little cooler up here.
地表温度可能会高到50摄氏度
Temperatures at ground level can reach
a blistering 50 degrees Centigrade.
幼鸟孵出后，会在巢里呆上六天
Once a chick hatches, it spends
the first six days in the nest.
这也是它们最脆弱的时候
This is when it's at its most vulnerable -
完全依赖父母
totally reliant on its parents.
强腐蚀性的烂泥能防御天敌
The caustic mud deters predators.
但成年的火烈鸟能行走自如，因为有细长的脚
But the adult flamingos can cope in this quagmire,
because of their long, scaly legs.
不小心从窝里滑出来的幼鸟
Any chick that slips from the nest, however,
行走在危险的地面
is treading on very dangerous ground.
它的家长鼓励它爬回去
This parent encourages her chick to climb back to safety.
抚养后代需要父母付出时间和精力
Raising chicks requires huge parental
investment in both time and labour,
无论你在哪里
wherever you are.
没地方比南极更为艰难
Few places are tougher than the Antarctic.
颊带企鹅
Chinstrap penguins.
它们每天去50英里外的海面捕食
Every day they travel up to 50 miles
out at sea, hunting for krill.
但困难的事情在于将食物带回栖息地
But the hard part is getting
this food back to the colony,
因为它位于一座环形大火山的顶部
because it sits on the ice-free rim at the
top of this giant volcano,Deception Island.
从捕鱼宴会返回，第一个挑战就是上岸
For the returning fishing party, the
first challenge is getting ashore.
海滩很陡峭，还有力道十足的回头浪
The beach is steep,with a powerful undertow.
这只雌企鹅安全登陆，开始一段漫长的徒步行走
This female lands safely, but she
now begins a long journey on foot.
对于不会飞的鸟，到达这座火山的顶部
For a flightless bird,getting to the top of the volcano
意味着一次艰难的爬行，特别是
means a gruelling climb,especially when glaciers,
面前的道路是泥泞的火山灰和冰雪混在一起
covered with muddy volcanic ash,stand in your way.
这就像一个蛇爬梯子的游戏
It's like a game of snakes and ladders.
依靠嘴巴、翅尖和脚趾的通力合作
A combination of beak,wing tip and feet.
它成功了！
And she wins through!
它遇到了企鹅的下班高峰期
Now she joins penguin rush hour.
几乎到家了
Almost home.
它到达火山口的边缘，但对它的考验还没有结束
She's reached the crater rim,
but her trials are still not over.
现在它必须在近15000只鸟中找到自己的家人
She must now try and find her family
among more than a 150,000 birds.
它的听觉如此敏锐，能在喧闹中识别出自己孩子独特的叫声
Her hearing is so acuteshe can identify
the individual cry of her own chick in the din.
它做到了，家人热烈地欢迎它的归来
She's made it and the family welcomes her return.
这一路的努力，回报是满嘴的磷虾
The result of all this parental effort - a mouthful of krill.
现在轮到它老公了
Now it's her partner's turn.
幼鸟的需求是无止境的
A chick's demands are endless.
有时候会把父母推向拼命的境地
Sometimes they can push parents to desperate lengths.
但鸟类是随机应变的大师
But birds are masters of improvisation.
南非Dassen岛，是大型白鹈鹕的栖息场所
Dassen Island, off the coast of South Africa, is home
to a nesting colony of great white pelicans.
这里无论大小，所有的幼鸟都胃口十足
There are chicks of all ages all with a hefty appetite.
它们的父母任务非常艰巨
The parents have a formidable task.
这些大鹈鹕是世界上最大的飞行鸟类之一，体重达10公斤
These pelicans are among the heaviest flying
birds in the world,weighing up to 10 kilos.
V字型编队是最省力的飞行方式
A V-formation is the most energy efficient means of flying.
能够为后面的鸟减少阻力
It significantly reduces drag for the bird behind.
鹈鹕通常沿着海岸捕鱼
Pelicans normally fish along the coast,
但食物的短缺迫使它们去别的地方寻找
but a shortage of food supplies
has forced them to look elsewhere.
角塘鹅
Cape gannets
扎入海水深处，在鹈鹕到不了的地方捕鱼
plunge deep, hunting fish beyond the reach of the pelicans.
但鹈鹕不是冲鱼来的
But the pelicans aren't after fish.
它们瞄着更大的家伙
Their sights are set on a bigger catch.
Malgas岛是6万只角塘鹅的栖息地
Malgas Island is the nesting ground
for some 60,000 Cape gannets.
通常，一只塘鹅外出觅食，另一只留下来照看幼鸟
Normally one gannet parent goes off fishing
while the other looks after the chick.
但鱼类资源的短缺意味着，有时候父母双方同时外出捕食
But declining fish stocks means both parents
are often away hunting at the same time,
留下幼鸟没人照看
leaving their chicks unguarded,
这一点没有逃过鹈鹕的注意
something which hasn't gone unnoticed by the pelicans.
那些有父母照看的
Only chicks with parents at their side,
或者太大而吞不下的，才得以幸免
or those too large to swallow,have a chance.
回到鹈鹕栖息地
Back at the pelican colony,
父母把消化得差不多的小塘鹅反刍一部分出来
the parents regurgitate partially-digested gannet chicks
喂养后代
for their brood.
几乎所有栖息在非洲海岸的鸟类数量都在减少
Although most seabird colonies on
the African Cape are in decline,
栖息在Dassen岛的大鹈鹕却在增加
the population of white pelicans
nesting on Dassen is growing.
当鸟儿们聚集在一起繁育
When birds come together to breed,
在它们把自己托付给另一方之前
and before they commit to one another,
通常会有引人注目的展示表演
they will often perform the most remarkable displays.
俄勒冈州的湖面上，最迷人的情景发生了
One of the most enchanting happens
here, on the lakes of Oregon.
克拉克e在寻找终生配偶，但雌性必须测试对方的承诺是否持久
Clarke's grebes mate for life,but the female must
test herpartner's continuing commitment,
她邀请他一起跳一支仪式化的舞蹈
and she does this by inviting him
to join her in a ritualised dance.
为了增进感情，他送给她一份礼物
To strengthen their bond,he offers her a gift.
现在，眼里只有对方
Now, with eyes only for one another,
这对忠诚伴侣的舞蹈进入了高潮
the faithful pair reach the climax of their dance.
有些鸟类并不结伴
Other birds don't form pairs.
相反，雄性试图尽可能地与多只雌性交配
Instead a male tries to mate with as many females as he can.
雄性松鸡聚集在怀俄明州的草地上
Male sage grouse gather in the grasslands of Wyoming
通过华美的羽毛和骄傲的姿态
to advertise their virility
宣告自己的男子气概
with a finery of feathers and proud posturing.
THEY MAKE POPPING SOUNDS
雌性看起来土里土气的
Females are much drabber-looking,
但是极端挑剔
but extremely choosy.
只会同最帅气的雄性交配
They will only mate with the most impressive male,
通过对方的嗓音来判断雄性的价值
and they judge a male's worthiness by the sounds he makes.
POPPING
鸟类在取悦异性方面真是不遗余力
Birds go to great lengths to impress their partners.
新几内亚丛林
In the forests of New Guinea,
它们以彩色的羽毛和优美的歌声来增强效果
they famously use colourful feathers and song to maximum effect.
BIRDSONG
鸟的天堂
Birds of Paradise.
但在这个岛屿的西部，这些爱炫耀的鸟
But in the western part of the island, these flamboyant birds
和另一种非常低调谦逊的鸟共处
share the forests with a rather unassuming-looking character...
Vogelkop造园鸟
the Vogelkop bowerbird.
也许羽毛并不出彩，但是它有非同寻常的歌唱本领
He might lack the plumage,but he's got an
extraordinary repertoire of song.
它也是出色的模仿家
And, he's a wonderful mimic.
HIGH-PITCHED SOUNDS
鸽子振翅的声音
Those are pigeon wing beats.
HIGH-PITCHED CALL
这是模仿虎皮鹦鹉
That's a modest tiger-parrot.
LOWER-PITCHED CALL
这个则是黄纹美冠鹦鹉
And that,a sulphur-crested cockatoo.
更令人惊讶的是，它是个热心的收藏家
Even more surprising he's an avid collector,
对色彩很有品位
with a very appreciative eye for colour.
这只雄鸟钟爱红色和橙色的花
This male favours red and orange flowers.
非常喜欢菌类
And he's very fond of fungus.
它搜集的每一样东西并非都呆着不动
Not everything he collects stays where it should.
它把这些宝贝陈列在花费几年时间造好的建筑物里面，或着放在周围
He puts these treasures on display within and around
a construction that has taken him years to build.
由一棵小树作支柱的大型房间，由苔藓铺成地毯
A giant bower woven around a central sapling, carpeted with moss.
这个宏大的设计不是作为巢穴
This grand design is no nest...
而是一个极具诱惑力的接待室
it's the ultimate seduction parlour.
但这个山坡上不止它一个
But he's not alone on this hillside.
在听得见的地方就有6个竞争对手
He's got six rivals within earshot.
这一只喜欢暗色调，用鹿粪球装饰自己的凉棚
This one prefers darker colours,
decorating his bower with deer dung.
还有木炭
And charcoal.
视觉效果是至关重要的
Visual effect is of crucial importance.
显然，它并没预料到这些萌发出来的菌类
Clearly he hadn't planned on all this sprouting fungus.
它和它的竞争对手们相距一箭之隔
He and his nearest rival live a stone's throw apart.
竞争很激烈
Competition is intense.
粪球凉棚最先引起雌性的注意
It's the dung-ball bower that is the
first to catch the female's attention.
它退在一旁，她来视察它的作品
He withdraws,while she inspects his workmanship.
她又回来了，看起来被吸引了
She's back again,and seems impressed.
但凑近一看，她又少了几分信任
But on closer inspection she is less convinced.
也许就因为那些讨厌的菌类！
Perhaps it was that sprouting fungus!
回到鲜花凉棚，雄鸟正在练习装扮
Back at the flower bower,the male performs a dress rehearsal.
它发觉雌鸟正在观看
He senses she's watching.
这正是它努力期待的时刻
This is the moment he's been working towards.
BIRD CALLS
它的凉棚将歌声朝她的方向传递
His bower channels his song in her direction.
MALE CALLS
最终的检查
A final check.
全是她所喜欢的
All is to her liking.
极少鸟类会为这个决定终生的时刻
付出如此多的技巧、精力和智慧
Few birds devote such craft,effort and ingenuity
to achieve this life-defining moment.
但在肯尼亚的Bogoria湖，大片的粉红色
But here on Kenya's Lake Bogoria,these massive pink slicks
预示着也许是自然界最大规模的求爱事件开始了
signal the start of perhaps the
grandest courtship event in nature.
在某些年份，当湖泊最为富饶的时候
In certain years, when the lake is at its richest,
超过1百万只火烈鸟来此聚集
more than a million lesser flamingos congregate to feed.
现在，首要的工作便是找到最佳情人
It's now, when they're in their prime, that they
must find their preferred partner.
为此，它们进行了一场引人注目的表演
To do that they perform a remarkable promenade.
头高举，颈部的羽毛皱起
With heads held high and neck feathers ruffled,
使它们看起来尽量的呈粉红色
making them look as pink as possible,
越来越多的鸟加入了这场求爱竞赛
more and more birds join in the courtship march
夫妻结对也开始了
and pairs begin to bond.
小群体合并成大群
Small groups merge with larger ones
上千只火烈鸟都行动着
until almost 1,000 flamingos are on the move.
从赤道到两极
From the equator to the poles,
鸟类找到了最为巧妙的方法
birds have found the most ingenious ways
来战胜生命中的诸多挑战
of overcoming the many challenges of life,
每一样都跟它们身上特有的羽毛相关
and everything revolves around
their unique attribute, feathers.
过去的三年来，Life制作组在能想到的地球每一个角落拍摄鸟类
For the past three years, the Life team has filmed
birds in every part of the world imaginable.
没地方比在巴布亚岛西部丛林拍摄更为棘手了
Nowhere was the filming trickier
than in the jungles of West Papua.
这里有对我来说，是鸟类中最有意思的景观
Here is found for me one of the greatest wonders
Vogelkop造园鸟的陈列展示竞赛
of the bird world, the display arena of the Vogelkop bowerbird.
13年前，我就曾有幸目睹它们的特殊作品
13 years ago I was lucky enough to
witness these spectacular builders,
但拍摄这种胆小的雌鸟以及它们的求爱行为则是另一回事情了
but filming the timid female and courtship
behaviour was a different matter.
这也是Life制作组动身前往的目的
And this was what the Life team set out to film.
Barrie Britton是这个项目的首席摄影师
Barrie Britton was the principle cameraman for this programme.
从事此道20多年
With over 20 years in the business,
他不仅是一位有才的摄影师
not only is he an accomplished
photographer
他这在这方面还有着深层次的理解，投入了很多感情
but he has developed a deep understanding
of and empathy for his subjects.
尽管每一项都会显现出它特殊的挑战
Although each one posed it's own unique challenges,
Barrie真的花了很多时间把自己藏在帐篷里进行拍摄
Barrie he did seem to spend an inordinate amount
of time cooped up in his trusty old hide.
想想也许我找错了隐藏地点，导致海水从帐篷下面漫上来
Think I may have misjudged the hide position, cos
the sea's coming in the bottom of the hide.
看，我在小帐篷里呆了11个小时
Well, that was 11 hours in my little box.
Barrie一路上都保持着勃勃的兴致直到最后
Barrie saved his most ambitious trip of the series until last.
摄制组一行40人花了三天时间跋涉，才抵达拍摄地点
It took a team of 40 people 3 days of tough
uphill trekking to get to the filming camp.
我本可以抱怨蚂蝗、咬人的虫子和艰难的进度
I could complain about leeches,biting insects, the tough going
但是，我不会，因为，这次不同寻常
but, I really don't want to,this is great.
看起来我走丢了，但我希望我的路是对的
Seem to have lost everyone else,I hope I'm going the right way.
噢，到了
Oh, made it.
实在是累
Completely shattered.
艰巨的工作才刚开始
The hard work had only just begun.
明天，组员们会在向导的带领下，寻找最好的窝拍摄
Tomorrow with the help of their guides, the crew
would go looking for the best bowers to film
但当地酋长告诉他们一个故事
but not before a cautionary tale from the local chief.
（他在讲本地话）
HE SPEAKS IN HIS OWN LANGUAGE
当他父亲第一次带他看那种“凉棚”
So when he first was shown the bower by his father
那里有很多花儿
he, there were flowers there,
他，一个12岁的小孩，想去摘那些花儿
and, as a 12-year-old child he wanted to grab them
但父亲立马制止了
but his father immediately stopped him
告诉他，不能碰“凉棚”里的任何东西，更不能拿走
and said, that he could not touch anything
or takeanything away from the bower
不然，立马就会天降暴雨
because otherwise it would start raining very heavily.
BEEPING
噢，Barrie，5点差十分了
Oh! It's ten to five, Barrie.
恩
Yep.
酋长的警告还在耳畔回荡
With the chief's warning fresh in their minds,
Barrie和他的小组一早出发去寻找“凉棚”
Barrie and the team make an early start and head for the hide.
我们正好赶在日出之前抵达，所以得尽快准备好
Well, we've reached the hide just at sunrise, so
we're just gonna get set up as quickly as we can.
在经验丰富的向导带领下，找到“凉棚”并不难
With knowledgeable guides, finding the bowers wasn't the problem.
谁会错过这么明显的建筑呢？
And who could miss such obvious structures?
现在，Barrie只能等待了
It was now a waiting game for Barrie,
躲在伪装过的帐篷里
heavily concealed in his camouflaged hide.
好了，6点半了
OK, it's 6.30,
我只是在等鸟的出现，并希望
so I'm just waiting now for the bird to come, hoping that
它不会发现这里有任何异样
he doesn't suspect that anything is here
然后我们能拍下它们自然的行为
and that we can get some natural behaviour.
BIRD CALLS
我刚听到帐篷右边有造园鸟的叫声
I've just heard the bowerbird call
just to the right of the hide.
RUSTLING
我能听见外面的鸟叫，它在拨弄帐篷表面的帆布
I can hear the bird outside, it's
plucking on the fabric of the hide.
我注意到它将帐篷底下的一块包装纸
I've just noticed that the bird
has pulled a Snickers wrapper out
扯了下来，拿回去展览了
of the bottom of the hide and has added it to its display.
这是个奇怪的装饰
It was a very strange decoration
我必须在天黑时将它移走
which I had to remove at the end of the day.
THUNDER
是Barrie不顾酋长的警告，冒不必要的险将那个包装纸拿走
Had Barrie tempted fate by removing the
wrapper and ignoring the chief's warning?
还是，这场雨只是雨林里司空见惯的？（雨林嘛）
Or was this just rainforest living up to its name?
像这样的磅礴大雨，拍摄已经不可能了
When it pours like this, filming becomes virtually impossible.
不久天气就转好了，Barrie又一次返回帐篷
Soon the weather improved and Barrie
returned once more to the hide.
这一次，他进行的很顺利
This time his lunch box was firmly sealed.
这只鸟很喜爱这种泛着金属光泽的小瓢虫
The bird is very keen on these
little tiny metallic ladybirds
而它们会从里面的位置爬出来
and they're a bit put out
being put there in this bower,
它们开始分散，慢慢地爬
so, they start crawling off,
they're very slowly making their way
爬过苔藓地毯，刚要爬出展览区域
over the moss and they just about
get to the edge of display
然后被造园鸟发现了，又把它们重新弄回去
and then the bowerbird notices and goes and
collects them and puts them back again,
所以，它们一次又一次地试图从造园鸟那里逃走
so they're kind of in this endless cycle of
trying to escape from the bower,
但它们永远也逃不掉
they're just, they can never quite get away.
对Barrie和雄鸟来说，雌鸟也是个大问题
However for the male bowerbird and Barrie
the female was still proving a problem.
雌鸟确实下来了，但它很警觉
The female did come down,but she was quite nervous
在接近凉棚入口处，我们不能靠的太近
near the entrance to the bower,
so we didn't get very much of that.
这真令人担心
This was a real concern,
因为我们故事的关键就是它们的求爱行为
because the courtship behaviour was key to our story.
他完成了10小时的工作
He's just done a 10-hour stint,
天气不错，所以我们希望一切顺利
been a really nice day so we're just hoping it's gone well.
又一天的拍摄结束了，但没什么值得表现的
Another day's filming over,
and still little to show for it.
在帐篷里呆10小时
10 hours in the hide.
幸好那天的拍摄结束了
Fortunately filming is over for the day,
我们准备走，又遇到了Barrie
we're just gonna go and collect Barrie again.
今天有拍到交配么？
Did you see a mate today?
没，没有
No, no, mating.
其它的都进展顺利，就是没拍到交配场面
Everything else is going well
but we haven't got the mating.
事实上，我已经取得不错的进展了，雄鸟已经明显习惯了帐篷
The fact I was getting such good footage of the
male meant he'd obviously got used to the hide.
但是来访的雌鸟还是对它很提防
But the visiting females were still wary of it.
雌鸟看起来很紧张，所以我决定把帐篷后移
The females did seem a bit nervous,so I
took the decision to push the hide back,
跟鸟儿们距离远一点，另外我还得调整镜头
just to get more distance from the birds, the
other thing I've done is recessed the lens
我们把这种植物放在镜头周围，希望雌鸟能更有表现
and we put this vegetation all around it, so I'm
hoping that's gonna provide more female behaviour.
拍摄只剩下几天了，对Barrie的考验到了紧要关头
There were few filming days left,it was
crucial Barrie's adjustments paid off.
雄鸟刚跑进凉棚，开始叫唤
The male has just run into the bower and started calling
所以我想，雌鸟可能要来了
so I think that means there might be a female coming.
我们在黑暗里等着
It struck me, here we both were waiting in the darkness,
雄鸟努力着吸引雌鸟
the male trying to attract the female,
我只希望没问题，雌鸟这次不会只是短暂的探访
and I was just hoping that I'd got it right this
time and it was more than just a fleeting visit.
在帐篷里静止不动呆了好几小时
Working in a hide involves hours of prolonged inactivity
被最为紧张的时刻打断了
punctuated by the most intense moments of action.
这是整个摄制组所期待的决定性时刻
This was the crucial moment the whole team had worked towards.
对Barrie来说，求爱行为
Everything was falling into place for Barrie,
有条不紊地进行着
the behaviour unfolding.
好，很好，我们开始拍了
Right, that's good,think we're in action.
在帐篷里呆了21天
21 days in a hide,
惊人的耐心和毅力
astonishing patience and perseverance.
这些以前从未被拍摄过
This has never been filmed before.
如此努力和付出只为那关键的几秒钟的行为
Such effort and endeavour for a crucial piece of
behaviour that's over in a matter of seconds.
Stephen，愿意和我握个手么？
Would you like to shake my hand, Stephen?
什么意思？   额，我们拍到了交配
What does that mean?
Well, we got the mating.
你们拍到了？   是的，拍到了
You got the mating?
Yeah, yeah, we got the mating.
哇哦，真是美好的一天，明亮的一天，太神奇了
Oh, wow.
Yeah, so really good day, brilliant day, yeah but just, just amazing.
我应该在这个帐篷里呆了三星期，我从没想过
I must have - well, what is it -three weeks I've
spent sitting in this hide, and I just didn't think
我们能拍到，因为我们没多少时间了……然后，这周就拍到了
we'd ever get it, cos we're running out of days, only
a few left now, so, so to get that this week is,
太不可思议了，真是太好了，我很高兴
is just incredible and it was a really, really good,
really good behaviour, so I'm delighted.
成功了！这是Barrie在鸟的这一集的最后一次拍摄
Success! This was Barrie's last filming trip for the Birds episode
多么好的一个结尾
and what a befitting end.